<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Full relation, not only of our good successe in generall, but how, and in what manner God hath fought his own cause miraculously, manifesting his mighty power by delivering the Protestants, miserably distressed under a cruell and most inhumane adversary. As also, the names of the chiefe commanders and officers in this late expedition of 3000. foote and 500. horse, under the command of the Earle of Ormond, lieutenant generall, and others mentioned more particularly in the relation. Published to prevent false and erronious copies which too often are set forth with mighty disadvantage to the truth it selfe.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84988</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860705</idno>
  <idno type="VID">112830</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240887739</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E145_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19624</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860705</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99860705e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84988)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112830)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 26:E145[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Full relation, not only of our good successe in generall, but how, and in what manner God hath fought his own cause miraculously, manifesting his mighty power by delivering the Protestants, miserably distressed under a cruell and most inhumane adversary. As also, the names of the chiefe commanders and officers in this late expedition of 3000. foote and 500. horse, under the command of the Earle of Ormond, lieutenant generall, and others mentioned more particularly in the relation. Published to prevent false and erronious copies which too often are set forth with mighty disadvantage to the truth it selfe.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Miller for W. Bladen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Ormonde, James Butler, --  Duke of, 1610-1688.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112830:1"/>
            <p>A FVLL RELATION, Not only of our good successe in generall, but how, and in what manner God hath fought his own cause miraculously, manifesting his mighty <hi>power by delivering the Protestants, miserably</hi> distressed under a cruell and most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Adversary.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, The Names of the chiefe Commanders <hi>and Officers in this late expedition of</hi> 3000. Foote and 500. Horse, under the command of the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lieutenant generall, and others mentioned more particularly in the Relation.</p>
            <p>Published to prevent false and erronious Copies which too often are set forth with mighty disadvantage to the Truth it selfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed <hi>G. Miller</hi> for <hi>W. Bladen,</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_commanders">
            <pb facs="tcp:112830:2"/>
            <head>The Names of the chiefe Commanders and Officers in this late expedition of 3000. Foote, and 500. Horse, under the command of the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> Lieutenant generall, are as followeth.</head>
            <p>THe chiefe Commanders were the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> Lord Lieutenant generall, next to him Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> of the Foote there was 600. of the Lord Generals Regiment, then under the command of Colonell <hi>Munck,</hi> 100. of the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Generals Regiment, then under the command of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Brunt Moore</hi> 400. of the Lord <hi>Lamberts</hi> Regiment, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of Sir <hi>Iohn Shurlock</hi> Lieutenant Colonell, 700. of Sir <hi>Charles Cootes</hi> Regiment, under his own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand 400. of the Regiment which was Sir <hi>Simon Harcotts,</hi> under the command of Sarjant Major <hi>Paggett</hi> 600. of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Craffords</hi> Regiment, under his own command, 100. of the Fierlocks under the command of Captaine <hi>Sandford:</hi> The 500. Horse, were under the command of Sir <hi>Richard Greenfield,</hi> Serjant Major of a Regiment of Horse, Sir <hi>Thomas Lucas</hi> Comissary generall of the Horse, Captaine <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> Captaine of the Lord Generals Troope, Sir <hi>George Wentworth,</hi> Sir <hi>Patrick Weymes</hi> Captaine of the Lord Lieutenant Generals Horses, Captaine <hi>Treswell,</hi> Captaine of the Lord <hi>Liles</hi> Troope, Captaine <hi>Armestrong</hi> Quartermaster generall, and Captaine <hi>Schoute,</hi> Captaine of 50. Volunteirs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112830:2"/>
            <head>A briefe Relation of the prosperous suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of our English Army, from their going out of <hi>Dublin, Aprill</hi> 2. 1642. till the 17. of the same that they returned thither againe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He 2. of <hi>Aprill</hi> being Saturday, our Army marched 6. miles to the Towne of <hi>Racoole</hi> where the two chiefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders with the foot companies were quartered, and all the Horse except Captaine <hi>Schouts</hi> troope, which that night lay at <hi>Kilmanham</hi> a mile from <hi>Dublin</hi> and came to <hi>Racoole</hi> the next morning before the Army was ready to march, were quartered in severall parts of the country therabouts.</p>
            <p>On the 3. of <hi>Aprill</hi> all the Army marched to the <hi>Naas</hi> being 6. miles the nearest way, but went on the left hand out of the way about 3. miles into the Country of <hi>Wicklow,</hi> burning houses, and killing such Rebels as they found stragling in the way, and comming within a mile of the <hi>Naas,</hi> one of our Trumpeters belonging to Sir <hi>George Went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> his Troop, was shot by the Rebels out of the Castle of <hi>Tipper,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall whereof some of our Souldiers blew up the Casile with 8 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels that were in it, with losse of 4. men, besides one that they lost in the way by pillaging. This night all the Army, except the Horse that were dispersed (as afore-said) were quartered at the <hi>Naas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 4. of <hi>Aprill</hi> the Army having fired houses in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> marched that day 8. miles to the Towne of <hi>Kilcullen,</hi> killing and hanging Rebels, and burning of houses, in the way the Troopes being quartered in severall places distant.</p>
            <p>The 5. of <hi>Aprill</hi> the Army marched 9. miles to the Towne of <hi>Athy,</hi> and in their way encamped neare a Castle of <hi>Ballysanon,</hi> belonging to one <hi>Fitz Garrald</hi> a Collonell of the Rebels, wherin there was 500 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels well armed, as was then informed, some of whom were seene on the top of the Castle, and their women all put out, and sitting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the side of the hill under the command of their shot; there the Army remained about 3. houres, during which time the Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> the Dutches, and the Earle of <hi>Castlehaven</hi> came in a Coach with 6. horses to the head of the Army, where they were received
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112830:3"/>with 3. shot of the field peeces for their welcome. And for their greater honour the Lieutenant Generall stood by the boot of the Coach, while the Army both horse and foot marched by them, and valed their Colours towards them, in regard his Lordship was there present, and so the Earle of <hi>Antrim</hi> and the rest in the Coach de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted home; and the Army having no battering peeces without any assault upon the Castle, continued their march to <hi>Athy,</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning houses and killing stragling Rebels, where they found the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of the Towne all burnt by the Protestants the day before, to prevent the Rebels, who in great multitudes had entered in and were about to fire the Castle-church, and other places, wherein the Protestants to the number of three hundred besides children were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served.</p>
            <p>The 6. of <hi>April</hi> 3. troops marched from <hi>Athy</hi> 7 miles to the Town of <hi>Caterlaugh,</hi> where <hi>Robert Harpoole, Walter Bagguall</hi> and other of the Rebels, had blockt up the Castle where the Protestants were, but upon the approach of our troops the Rebels burnt the Towne and fled away, but our troopes in pursuit of them, slew about 60. tooke great store of Corn, Cattle and other provision with which they relieved the Castle; and having furnished them with ammunition, the said troops likewise releeved Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> Castle that stands upon the same ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver some 2. miles from <hi>Catherlagh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same day others of the Army marched to the Castle of <hi>Balli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> in the possession of Captaine <hi>Grymes,</hi> who having, during the Rebellion, held the same against the Rebels, and therein besides Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers maintained 250. poore distressed Protestants at his own charge, was then besieged by the Rebels with a 11. colours and a 100. horse, that at sight of that party of our Army fled away: The same day in the morning Sir <hi>John Bowen</hi> came to our Army in <hi>Athy</hi> in as consident a manner, crying welcome, welcome Gentlemen, as if he had bin an innocent person, but he being strongly suspected of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, was by Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> committed to prison; and the same day part of our Army marched to his Castle of <hi>Ballyadams</hi> 4. miles from <hi>Athy,</hi> where his Lady entertained them liberally, and in shew heartily with ale and cakes, from whence our Army drove about 200 head of Cattell, and a 1000. sheep to <hi>Athy,</hi> and left the Major, Sir <hi>Richard Greenfield</hi> with his troope there for a time in garrison; so that now the Towne of <hi>Athy</hi> being in great distresse through want of meat and drinke was partaker of such plenty, that a Lambe Was sold for 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg>.</p>
            <p>On the 7. of <hi>Aprill, George Walker</hi> son of English Parents, then
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112830:3"/>soveraigne of <hi>Athy,</hi> with many other Rebels being hanged, all our Army except Collonell <hi>Crafford</hi> and that part of his Regiment then under his command, and Sir <hi>George Wentworths</hi> troope marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Marryborowas</hi> fort of Lease, and in the way the cheefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders with the foot companies lay at <hi>Stratbelly</hi> about 5. miles from <hi>Athy</hi> and the troopes in severall quarters thereabouts.</p>
            <p>The 8. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> the Army marched to <hi>Maryborrow</hi> about foure miles, except Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> with his troop, the Lord <hi>Liles</hi> troop, Sir <hi>Thomas Lucas</hi> and Captaine <hi>Schouts</hi> troope that parted from the Army at Sir <hi>Robert Piggots</hi> house 2. miles before they came to the Fort and from thence marched 10. miles further to relieve the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants in the Towne of <hi>Ballanokell,</hi> which troopes being infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that 300. of the Rebels were about a mile from <hi>Ballanokell</hi> marching from the Castle of <hi>Knockard</hi> belonging to <hi>Barnaby Demp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie</hi> towards <hi>Ballanokell</hi> to intercept our troopes, S. <hi>Charles</hi> rid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them and viewing, of them, lead up the Lord <hi>Liles</hi> troope onely, being then in the vann, and fell upon them so couragiously and unexpectedly that they were presently put to rout, and with that single troope, slew about 50. of the Rebels, took some of their Armes and 2. Prisoners, and put the rest to flight, where our men could not follow them, they taking the Castle and boggs for their succour, wherein none of our men were lost or hurt, only one <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> a Scottish Gentleman that was our guide, and not otherwise un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der command was shot in the Arme: that execution being done, we matched into the Towne of <hi>Ballanokell,</hi> where we found 600. Protestants unspeakably rejoycing at our approach, they having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that lost 140 by the Flucks and other diseases through want of fire and other necessaries, which they could not procure before for want of ammunition; in this Towne they had banished away all Papists, because they found them perfidious and treacherous, and from hence the two prisoners being hanged, our troopes the same night marched backe to the said Towne of <hi>Maryborrow,</hi> whether they by reason of the darkenesse of the night and their carriage came not till 2. of the clocke in the morning, in which Towne they found the poore Protestants in want of all outward comforts, and so unable to relieve the Army either foot or horse, there being neither bread nor drinke, hay nor oates for many, in which Towne the 2. chiefe Commanders and the foot companies were quartered and the troops in places distant therabouts.</p>
            <p>The 9. of <hi>Aprill</hi> orders were given for all the troops to be in readinesse the next morning at 2. of the clock in <hi>Marybrorow.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112830:4"/>
            <p> The 10. of <hi>Aprill</hi> being <hi>Easter-day,</hi> the said troopes being in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse according to order, Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> with his troope, Sir <hi>Richard Greenfield,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Lucas,</hi> Captaine <hi>Yarner,</hi> Captaine <hi>Armestrong</hi> and Captaine <hi>Schout</hi> with their troopes, and about 20. Musketiers with Carrages, marched towards <hi>Barr</hi> against <hi>Parsonstowne</hi> 23. miles, they being in their way to relieve the <hi>Burr</hi> 13. miles from the fort, and the Castle of Captaine <hi>Peaslies,</hi> as also the said Towne of <hi>Burr;</hi> in which march S. <hi>Charles Coote</hi> with 28. chosen out for to be the forlorne hope, marched first a good space before the said troopes, and in their way through the woods of <hi>Mouatrath</hi> above 2 miles loag, whence it was impossible for us to march, had the Rebels expected our comming on that day, the forlorne hope was stayed in the said wood with a great tree, which the Rebels had cut downe and laid over crosse a River, through which they were to passe, at which time the troopes in the forlorne hope, by reason of the extremity of cold and continuall raine that fell that Morning till twelve of the clock, being slacke to wade into the river to remove away the tree; Sir <hi>Charles</hi> himselfe taking notice therof, entred the River first over his boots, and to the middle of his Armes in water, laid hold of the tree, at sight whereof every one strove, who could first be at the worke, and so instantly cleared the passage, against the body of the troopes approached; in these woods divers Rebels were to keep by the forlorne hope unexpectedly, and being examined by Sir <hi>Charles,</hi> were meritoriously not deprived only of their estates but lives also, the rest of the troopes that followed, were encountred with such of the Rogues in the interim betweene the passage of the forlorne hope, and the rest of the troopes make head with divers shot out of the woods, on each side with Rebels with twelve Carabines of Captain <hi>Schouts</hi> troope, sent out by their Captaine by order from <hi>S. Thomas Lucas</hi> were slaine and put to flight, yet notwithstanding the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne hope having marched about a bow-shot from the said wood, were in their way at the side of a bogg, beset by Collonell <hi>Bryan,</hi> who himselfe upon a brave Horse with a buff-coat with silver lace, and his glittering Pistoll in his hand, with a file of Musketeers on foot that issued from the rest of the Rebels, strongly intr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nched in and Irish house in the bottome of a hill, called to the Cornet of Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> his troope, who was then in the head of the forlorne hope, saying come hither, come hither red cap; at which time the said Sir <hi>Charles</hi> being gone backe towards the body of our troope, the said Cornet with 8. Catrabines of the forlorne hope, rid down the hill towards the said Rebels, to charge upon them, but the said
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112830:4"/>Colonell with the rest of his Musketeers ranne into their trenches, and immediately after the said Sir <hi>Charles</hi> having notice of the said Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, he with the rest of the troopes then behinde, marched up to the top of the hill about Musket-shot, distant from the place where the Rebels were intrenched, and having drawne them into a body S. <hi>Charles</hi> himselfe with the same 8. Carrabiners of the forlorne hope, rid downe the hill towards the Rebels, and comming neare to the house he found no passage but through a narrow lane, where on both sides in the fields the Rebels lay in the ditches with their Muskets ready charged, to cut off as many as came that way, which they might doe without feare of any hurt to themselves, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he and the rest returned to the troopes againe, and the 6. trumpets being sounded on our side, to invite the Rebels to sight, they would not come out of their holes, untill S. <hi>Charles</hi> with a Musket on his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der on foot and a file of his owne dragoners on foot with their Muskets marched downe the hill, on the out-side of the lane, and fell upon the Rebels, beat them into the house and seattered them upon the boggs, where our men could not follow them, killed some of them.</p>
            <p>And thereby having cleared our passage, the said troupes with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne hope before them lead up by the said Sir <hi>Charles</hi> about 12. of the clocke, matched forward on the journey with much rejoycing, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard at that instant the raine ceased, and the Sunne began gloriously to shine, and having marched about halfe a mile further, they perceived on the top of a Castle a little above Musket-shot from them, on their right hand many Rogues issuing out and returning in, and one of them with a rich suite, a glittering head-peace, and his drawne sword invited our men to fight with them; but our men going on their journey about halfe a mile farther, were to passe over a great bogg through a narrow plash or Causie, where but one horse at a time could passe, which Causie the Rebels had barrow caded with a trench of Earth, out of which they shot fiercely upon us; but the Dragoneers of Captaine <hi>Armestrongs</hi> his Company, with 20. Musketiers led up by Sir <hi>Charles</hi> and the said Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine drove the Rogues out, and killed 8 of them in the bogg; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides their Captaine <hi>William Fitz Patricke,</hi> brother to the great Colonell, <hi>Fitz Patricke,</hi> with a Lieutenant and a piper, and the rest vanished without any further resistance, and being pursued by our men many of them were slaine as is conceived to the number of 40. up and downe the boggs and sides thereof, and that without hurt of any of our men, only Captaine <hi>Amestrong</hi> was shot on his belly through his cloathes, and shirt without danger, his skin not being broken. From thence our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112830:5"/>troups marched to <hi>Burrows</hi> burning all before them till they came there, and having relieved that Castle where the Protestants for 17. weeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore durst not issue out a stones cast to fetch in a sticke of wood to burne, they marched towards the <hi>Burr,</hi> 10. miles further, whither they came not till 3. of the clocke next Morning, in regard of the carriage which they carried along with them, and also of the great numbers of the Rebels which then were making head against us in the night we were constai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to goe farre about there then the Rebels expected, and so relieved both <hi>Peslies</hi> house, and the <hi>Burr</hi> without any further resistance. At our comming into the <hi>Burr</hi> we found the Protestants there exceedingly revived at the sight of us; but in great want, there being neither provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for man or beast for any money except in the Castle, for some of the chief of their Commanders and their horses. About four of the clock order was given to our tropes to march backe again, although out horses were almost spent, and our selves wearied out for want of sleep so as in the night we could not see the Firmament, but like a wall before us, whereon the shadow of our selves and horses in shew appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the ground on which we rid seemed to move under us, however the command was reasonable and necessary, because we by staying might give the Rebels such advantage as no passage could be gained: And about five of the clocke we marched from <hi>Burr,</hi> and about two miles off we for an houres time baited our horses with some Oates in the sheafe, and they marched forward another way to the <hi>Burr</hi> by Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> his house, called Castle Cuffe which the daye before the Rebels, in revenge of the death of their Captaine <hi>Fitz Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricke</hi> had burned, our Army being then to march through a wood, the Rouges had gathered great forces together there, as also at the bogg of <hi>Capper-beg</hi> to cut of all our troupes, they being places of great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to them in regard our men could not march above 3. abreast, of which we having some intelligence by one of the Rebels which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken prisoner, as he stood Sentinell we put our troupes in Battalia, and sounded our Trumpets together, in the meane while the Rouges shot at us out of the bushes and thickets of the wood and the ditches many dangerous shots, where Captaine <hi>Yarner</hi> was shot in the head, but not much hurt more then the raising of his skin. Also Captaine <hi>Schouts,</hi> Quarter-master was shot on side of his breast, but preserved from hurt by his armour and Buff-coat, and the rest of the trope wonderfully delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from their enemies, Whereupon the Rebels continually discharging upon us, our men seeing the great disadvantage they sustained by reason they could not see their enemies, to avoid them, or to charge upon them, they resolved to fight it out to the last man, leaving all their carriage and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112830:5"/>baggage behinde them, with a guarde till the event of the battle was knowne, and so they drew up our Horse from the causie or pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage into a field or side of a hill in the wood on the right hand, to encounter the rogues, who discharged against them, out of the wood on their left hand, at which time Sir. <hi>Charles Coote</hi> with the rest of the Captaines then present, having passed a few words in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conference, Sir <hi>Charles</hi> led a party of dragoneers on foot, with their Muskets downe the hill, over crosse the Lane, who according to his directions, shot into the woods at randome, untill they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the same places out of which the Rebels discharged, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many of the Rebels were killed, and the rest disperced into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the woods and boggs, without losse or hurt of any of our men; in the meane while our troope marched through the said wood towards the Towne of <hi>Ballycolly, alias Mountmelick,</hi> burning all before us on that side, and also the same day Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Munck</hi> issued, out of <hi>Maryborrow</hi> with about 500. foot and a 100. Horse to meet Sir <hi>Charles,</hi> and having marched towards <hi>Partnehinch</hi> to a strong Castle of one <hi>Daniels</hi> neare thereunto, held by the Rebels, he found them there and at <hi>Partnehinch</hi> so strongly fortified with barracadoes and halfe moones, that they could doe no good against the rogues, and so the day being farre spent, he not expecting the comming of Sir <hi>Charles</hi> so late that night, marched backe to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryborrow,</hi> having slaine severall Rebels with losse of 2. or 3. of our men, burned severall houses, which our troops in the Evening per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but could not tell whether our friends or enemies had done it, in regard none of our Army from <hi>Maryborrow,</hi> as we expected, met us, when our troopes came to <hi>Ballycolly,</hi> they could not passe through the Towne, by reason the bridge was broken and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels strongly fortified there, but were constrained both horse and carriage to march on the back side of the Towne on the right hand, about Musket-shot at the edge of the Evening over a deepe forde and through a boggy wood, continuing neare halfe a mile in length, where we stayed above an houre before we could get a guide to bring us out, and in the meane time set severall houses in the Town and in the wood on fire, by the light whereof we got cleare, and about halfe a mile from that place, in the way to <hi>Maryborrow,</hi> about 10. of the clock in a darke night, wee found the way barrowcadowed with Earth, and a deepe ditch and 2. boggs before it, where we stood neare 4. hours before it could be made passable, in which passage through the boggs 6. or 7. of our horses were lost, and all our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiage with a guard, forced to stay in a dangerous manner till the next
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112830:6"/>Morning, and the horse that got over this passage rid to the Town of <hi>Maryborrow</hi> in greater danger, though he knew it not then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, because they marched in severall companies to <hi>Maryborrow</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of 4. or 6, or 7. at a time, as also in the way there being a woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den bridge over a deepe water, which bridge the Rebels had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe, by reason whereof divers of our men had like to have bin drowned, as also the Rebels had built a Sconce on the left hand on the side bridge, within halfe Musket-shot of it, in the nature of a halfe moone, where 30. men would discharge at once, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no way for our men to avoide their shot, in regard the water is not passable any where, but betwixt the bridge and the said Sconce, however at last our men came safe to the rest of the Army at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryborrow</hi> about 3. of the clock in the Morning, without losse of one man, wherein the great mercy and wonderfull power of God is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seene if we consider these 3. particulars.</p>
            <p>First, the power of our enemies in that place, who withstood our Army and remained in their Forts securely till the Army that met us was returned backe to <hi>Maryborrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The wearinesse of our men, and weaknesse of our horse, who had marched 48. houres together without any rest more then three houres.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The severall advantages the enemy had against us in number and in places, as woods, waters, boggs, trenches and halfe moones, they having no cause to depart, but that the Lord by a causlesse feare removed them out of our way, and hereby preserved us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</p>
            <p>On the 12. of <hi>Aprill</hi> the troops were dispersed into their severall quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters about <hi>Maryborrow</hi> as before.</p>
            <p>This day the Rebels with 34. Colours in sight, being at the Bridge of <hi>Mageny,</hi> two miles from <hi>Athy,</hi> which the Protestants formerly had broken downe to prevent the incursions of the Rebels upon them, were repairing the same with 700. men, to make good the passage, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to march over it, and unexpectedly to intercept our Army in their returne from <hi>Maryborrow</hi> to <hi>Athy;</hi> but the Rebels were hindered by Colonell <hi>Crafford,</hi> who upon notice given him, suddenly with about 30. Dragoners, and 30. Horse of Sir <hi>George Wentworths</hi> troupe marched thither, and beat the 700. Rebels off and from the Bridge, killed one or two of them without the losse of any of ours, onely one of ours was shot on the backe and belly without any hurt, and so made good the Bridge till Evening, that he retreated backe to <hi>Athy,</hi> in regard many of the Rebels on horsebacke had forded the River, and were like to have surprized him.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112830:6"/>
            <p> On the 13<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. of the same, the said troupes with the rest of the Army there marched to <hi>Athy,</hi> where the foot were quartered, and the troupes dispersed into severall places distant from the Towne.</p>
            <p>On the 14<seg rend="sup">•h</seg>. of <hi>April</hi> all the troupes according to order marched to <hi>Athy,</hi> and from thence some of them with divers principle Officers, attended the Lord Lievtenant Generall, and Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> to the said Bridge of <hi>Mageny,</hi> to view the Rebels Army then incamped on both sides, neere to Captaine <hi>Erasmus Burrowes</hi> house, and from thence returned that night backe againe, resolving to march to <hi>Dublin</hi> without stirring out of the way, unlesse the Rebels did encounter us.</p>
            <p>On the 15<seg rend="sup">t•</seg> of <hi>April</hi> one <hi>Brocke</hi> an English Papist, of whom the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt part of the Protestant Clergy thereabouts made great use of in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times for vexing of the honest Clergy-men and their hearers, with divers other Rebels were hanged: The number of Rebels hanged du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of our Army being there is conceived to be about 70. The same day our Army having left at and about <hi>Athy</hi> Captaine <hi>Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Burrowes,</hi> Captaine <hi>Grimes,</hi> Captaine <hi>Thomas Welden,</hi> and the two Captaine <hi>Piggots</hi> with their Compaines, 300. whereof is part of our Army, we marched againe with Sir <hi>John Bowen, Fitz Garrald</hi> of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moga, Richard Grace</hi> of <hi>Mary-borrow,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Crosby</hi> prisoners towards <hi>Dublin.</hi> And in the way about two miles from <hi>Athy,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels appeared in great multitudes, to the number of 800 foot, and three or foure troupe of horse in a furious march, for three miles toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the right hand of us, there being a bogge between us, labouring at the end of the bogge to get the advantage of the ground and wind of our Army, which they accordingly did, and so at <hi>Black-hale Heath,</hi> on the lands of <hi>Killerush,</hi> about five miles from <hi>Athy,</hi> and a mile from the said Castle of <hi>Ballysanan,</hi> in the possession of Colonell <hi>Fitz Garrat</hi> the Rebell, and neare unto the place where the Earle of <hi>Autrim</hi> liveth, the Rebels made a stand, and set themselves in Battalia, with the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of two great ditches on each wing, so high that we could see no more then the heads of their pikes; and with such a hill before them, betwixt them and us, that we could scarcely see their Colours, as also with the wind on their backs, and a great bogge about a mile behind them: And besides their multitudes they were exceeding well armed, all their horses and men fresh, whereas our men and horses were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most worne out, and were now to march against them up hill, and over plowed land and ditches: However the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> seeing them stand, did most couragiously and instantly set our Army in Battell-aray, with their faces towards the Rebels.</p>
            <p>The Army of the Rebels was composed of the chiefest men in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112830:7"/>Counties of <hi>Kilkeny, Queens County, Catherlagh, Wexford, Wicklow, Kildare,</hi> and other severall parts in the Province of <hi>Lemster,</hi> and also in the Counties of <hi>Tipperary,</hi> and <hi>Waterford,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Munster.</hi> The chiefe Commanders were the Lord <hi>Mongarratt Pursell,</hi> Barron of <hi>Laughmore, Hewmac Philem Burne,</hi> Lieutenant Generall of the <hi>Limster</hi> forces, Colonell <hi>Toole,</hi> Colonell S. <hi>Morgan Canaugh,</hi> Col<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nell <hi>Moris Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naugh, Arthur Caanaugh,</hi> with Colonell <hi>Bagnall,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Dun boyne,</hi> Colonell <hi>Roger More,</hi> and many other of the principle Rogues: Those of <hi>Tripperary</hi> were commanded by <hi>Pursell,</hi> those of <hi>Wicklow</hi> by <hi>Hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack Philem Burne,</hi> those of <hi>Waterford</hi> by Colonell <hi>Moris Canaugh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rebels having so stood for a quarter of an houre, our Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prepared to encounter them, the forlorne hope consisting of 150. Musketiers, who marched first up the hill fiercely discharging upon them, and was seconded by Captaine <hi>Sandford</hi> with his fire locks, that led up the Right-hand-wing in the Vann, who followed him close, and charged them fiercely; The field-pieces likewise continually playing upon them, stroke the Rouges into such a feare, that some of the Pikes began to retreat: At sight whereof a great shout was in our Army in derision, crying, O hone, O hone, O hone, and the Rebels still dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging, though faintly against our men. Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> ordered the Reare, consisting of 3. troupes, <hi>viz.</hi> the L. <hi>Liles,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Grienfields,</hi> Captaine <hi>Schouts,</hi> to stand on the right hand of the right wing of our fooot then in the Vann about musket shot from the left hand of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels then in the Vann, and in like manner commanded the Vann, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of 6. troupes more, <hi>viz.</hi> S. <hi>Thomas Lucas</hi> the Lieutenant Generall, taine <hi>Yarner,</hi> Sir <hi>George Wentworth,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Armestrongs</hi> were commanded to stand on the left hand: During which time, Sergeant Major <hi>Pagett</hi> with 3. Compaines of the Regiment, heretofore under the command of Sir <hi>Simon Harcott,</hi> who led up the left hand wing in the Vann, advanced boldly, and stoutly discharged upon the Rebels. And Colonell <hi>Crafford</hi> also, with his part of Regiment, who marched in the body of the Vann, seconded him with such speed, courage, and resolution that he gained the front, and so our men approaching neare unto the Rogues, and about 10. shot out of the field-pieces being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged against them, they, although by reason of the hill had lost but few men, through feare fled away, after whom Sir <hi>Charles</hi> rode with such speed that his can falling off, he would not spend time to put it on, but rid bare-headed after them. At this time of said 3. troupes in the Reare, led by the Major of the horse, and the 6. troupes in the Vann led up by by Sir <hi>Thomas Lucas,</hi> fell most furiously pell mell upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, killing and destroying them till they were out both of themselves
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112830:7"/>and their horses in doing execution upon the Rogues. The foot also pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing them into severall houses and cottages in which they fled for suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, killed about 100. of them, and so both horse and foot continued execution untill the Rebels that were left alive were got out of reach into boggs and holes where we could not follow them, crying, O hone, O hone, O hone; some bewayling the losse of Fathers, some of Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, some of their Cousins, and others of their Masters and friends, in the which sight there was at the least 500 of the Rebels shine upon the ground, which have cost our Army a great deale of paines, the Rogues being long in dispatching, some of them abiding 2. or 3. shot before they would fall, besides many that ran away over the boggs in the crowde after they were shot by our horse and foot, which by some, according to intelligence from the Rebels, since the battell, are dead, to the number of 500. or 1000. more. We likewise tooke 15. of the Rebels Colors, 10. of which was rent of standard, and secretly, though unadvisedly conveyed away by those of our men that tooke them, the other 5. were brought to <hi>Dublin,</hi> with three heads of the principall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels: In one of the Colours there is three Pictures, one of the Trinity in visible shapes, and of <hi>Joseph,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> and Christ, like a childe in one place: The second is of <hi>Mary Magdalen:</hi> The third of S. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricke,</hi> however as those Pictures could not deliver them, so it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Lord <hi>Mongarratt</hi> durst not trust them, because he stood in a bogg to see what would be the event of this battell. We tooke great store of Armes from the Rogues, as Head-pieces, breast and backe parts, Harquebusiers, Muskets, Fowling pieces, Caleevers, Horses, Carra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, Pistols, Swords, Skeens, Pikes and Darts in abundance, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Lord <hi>Mountgarrats</hi> carriage, and his 8. Oxen that drew it, his Sump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Sumpter horse, and Daughters cloathes, with what store of Pouder and Amunition they had left this day. One of the Rogues being taken prisoner, and being examined by some of our Commanders, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed that two dayes before, all the Commanders of the Rebels sate in Councell, and upon debate of many propositions, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> amongst other things, it was finally concluded and agreed, that upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of our Army, of which they made no doubt, they were to give no quarter to any, except the Commanders of the field, being only the Lord Lieutenant Generall, the Colonels, Lieu. Colonells and Serjeant Majors, and all the rest, as well Captaines as others, to be put to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent execution, and then after the said conquest they were to besiege the City of <hi>Dublin:</hi> The substance of which examination is confirmed by severall Letters taken out of the pockets of Colonell <hi>Moris Caanagh</hi> by one of Captaine <hi>Schouts</hi> troop who killed him, which Letter was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112830:8"/>delivered by the said Captaine unto the Lord Lieutenant Generall: It likewise appeared that the said Rebels on the day of battell perceiving the couragious marching of our Army were once before the battell, as the prisoner declared, resolved not to give battell that day; but when they observed our Army so, halfe an houre together marched fast, beyond their expectation, changed their mind, conceiving our Army was fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and so gave us battell, intending to over-run us with their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes the first time they should find our Army disordered, they being for number neare three men for one of ours, and this day did the goodnesse of God appeare in the defence and preservation of his cause and people, by giving a few weake and wearied men and horse victory against the creame of all the Rebels forces, so well armed and strengthened with so many advantage, and that only with the losse of about 10. common soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and hurt of one Captaine, and about 15. souldiers of whom there is no feare. This night the Vann of our Army lay at old <hi>Connell,</hi> the rest on the Corrough of <hi>Kildare</hi> all in the open field.</p>
            <p>On the 16<seg rend="sup">•h</seg>. of <hi>April</hi> the Army marched to the <hi>Naas,</hi> where the chief Commanders with the foot were quartered, and the troops dispersed into severall parts distant thereabouts.</p>
            <p>On the 17<seg rend="sup">•h</seg>. of <hi>April</hi> being Sunday, Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment and two troops, remained at the <hi>Naas,</hi> and the rest of the Army marched to <hi>Dublin</hi> in safety, with great joy to the Protestants, and griefe to the Papists. From all which passages we have just grounds of thankfulnesse to God, yet no ground to conclude that the Rebels are vanquished, but contrariwise that their running into Woods, Boggs, and Castles will prolong the warre, and bring us all to ruine, unlesse this Summer in due time we be furnished out of <hi>England</hi> with great store of men and of money, to maintaine garrisons in all places, to cut off these cowardly Rebels like snakes when they peep out of their holes, that so the Land may be inhabited, and the profit thereof reaped by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Loyall Subjects, which otherwise cannot but in vaine be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112830:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>